Cooper Chien, MBA, PMP

San Francisco Area | kc937@cornell.edu | 626.927.8784 | www.linkedin.com/in/cooperchien

Senior IT Leader Executive Summary

Business/customer-focused technology executive with master's degree in computer science, MBA from Cornell, 20+ years of IT experience including 10 years of progressive leadership in building global teams and infrastructure. Adept at aligning technology investments with organizational goals and driving innovation to support business growth and operational excellence based on my 5S principles: Stability, Security, Speed, Scalability, and Sustainability.

Collaborative team builder cultivated a high-performing, customer-centric IT organization through servant leadership. Transformed IT from reactive to proactive innovators by prioritizing talent development successfully in enterprises.

- Drove scaled growth and maturity for IT operational excellence, security posture, and budget model at Amyris.
- Led IT innovation, software development, and operations/services launch at Amazon HQ, including Amazon Robotic Fulfillment Center, Amazon Fresh, and AWS Data Centers.
- Completed \$8 million US IT digital transformation and Zero-Trust security implementation at Huawei Technologies.

Professional Experiences

Amyris Inc. (NASDAQ: AMRS), Emeryville, CA

07/2021 - 02/2024

Vice President of Information Technology

Hired 3 managers, led a team of 40 IT staff, managed a \$20M budget, and launched a 24/7 incident support operation for a global biotech firm with offices in the USA, EU, and Brazil. Optimized IT operational costs through strategic vendor negotiations, cloud cost optimization, and process automation.

- Strategically Scaled IT organization by 3x to achieve business expansion goals and M&A integrations.
 - Established robust KPIs with C-suite team, and aligned company strategy to establish IT governance frameworks, policies, and procedures.
 - Collaborated with cross-functional teams to evaluate and implement Al-powered solutions, including a Gen Al Chatbot, which reduced IT ticket volume by 10% and boosted service satisfaction by 9%.
 - Spearheaded the implementation and integration of enterprise systems, including Salesforce CRM and Oracle NetSuite, streamlining business processes and enhancing data-driven decision-making.
 - Lowered cloud operating costs by 28%, IT incidents by 80% and decreased change management issues by 70% in my 1st year. Empowered shared service to automate processes, saving 400 labor hours monthly.
- Infused innovative and entrepreneurial spirit into team DNA, shifting IT service from reactive to proactive.
 - Established an IT PMO and instituted Agile methodologies to accelerate the delivery of in-house software solutions by 20%, develop data dashboards for efficient decision-making, and simplify business processes.
 - Enabled 31% eCommerce revenue growth with implementation of new subscription models, web UX improvements, and influencer management solutions; earned Revenue Milestone Award.
- Matured IT governance capabilities and security resilience with new applications, processes, and configurations.
 - Implemented a library system that automatically managed ISO 27001, SOC2, and SOX evidence collection and document updates, ensuring full compliance while minimizing manual monitor hours.
 - Conducted comprehensive cybersecurity audits and training; led vulnerability remediation and security hardening to cut security risk by 70% in one quarter.

Huawei Technologies, Santa Clara, CA

09/2017 - 07/2021

Information Technology Director (US IT Infrastructure & Operations Role)

Recruited to revitalize US IT function and realign IT strategies to meet evolving business needs. Led a team of 2 project managers and 20+ IT staff, while supervising managed services supporting 12 US locations and IT programs.

- **Directed IT transformation** including collaborating with HR to implement Workday HCM and transition a \$2.2 million IT contractor model from staff augmentation to managed service.
 - Earned **Future Star Award** for achieving 91% service satisfaction rate in the first year.
 - Revamped PMO, reducing project budget errors by 80% and scope creep by 50%.
- Led \$8 million portfolio to rebuild Huawei US business services during the US/China trade war and COVID.
 - Migrated R&D and 20+ apps to SaaS and AWS. Ended co-location data center contract, saving \$3 M.

Cooper Chien Page 2 | kc937@cornell.edu | 626.927.8784

Amazon (NASDAQ: AMZN), Seattle, WA

06/2014 - 09/2017

Technical Program Manager | IT Manager

Recruited as IT Manager leading Amazon eCommerce R&D IT team, promoted to Technical Program Manager to lead AWS R&D programs covering product development, efficiency improvement, and security initiatives.

- Launched flagship Robotic Fulfillment Center, collaborating with construction, Amazon Robotics, security, eCommerce operation, and supply chain teams. Hired and led IT team to deliver 1 million-square-foot facility with 5,000 robots, 21 IDFs, 1,200 wireless access points, and 4,500 employees across 4 floors in 8 months. Received Manager Award for Customer Obsession.
- Led strategy and launch of Prime Now Fulfillment Center in just 8 weeks, driving network and security design optimization and on-time, on-budget delivery of IT infrastructure to enable customer order delivery within 2 hours.
- Developed an RPA algorithm to reduce shipping box waste by 8% by optimizing the robots' fulfillment process, consolidating multiple shipments to the same address into one.
- **Led global cross-functional AWS IT programs**, involving Legal, Procurement, Finance, Operations, & Engineering to identify opportunities and execute innovation from concept to prototype to production.
 - Customized AWS Power Transfer Switch, saving \$50M per year in direct costs, eliminated 80% of risks,
 - Onboarded 1st generation AWS Water Filtration System, cutting water expenses by >15%.
- Championed series of solution innovation programs; designed new server room cooling solution to cut energy costs 30%, leveraged automation to optimize labor tracking, and printer ticket resolution processes globally.

Clinisys/Atlas Development, CALABASAS, CA

02/2007 - 06/2014

Senior Manager, Data Center Infrastructure & Operations

Expanded IT team to include 6 engineers based in the US and 4 in India, launched a co-location data center in Las Vegas, and established an infrastructure performance monitoring system for a healthcare data software company.

- Rapidly turned around major at-risk healthcare project for LA County outbreak detection system; cut technical
 risk by 90%; improved communication/trust proactively; expanded program to San Diego County.
- **Disaster recovery**: Led a private cloud disaster recovery solution from inception to go-live in <100 days. Improved ROI by utilizing a backup environment as a test environment, allowing developers to run tests on the most updated system, saving \$300K.

Additional Experiences

Datavo Inc., Senior Manager, Network & Infrastructure 09/2005 – 02/2007 Flextronics International/Gtran Wireless, IT Manager, Infrastructure & Application 02/2002 – 09/2005 Intecs International, Network Administrator 11/2000 – 02/2002

- Redesigned data stack architecture at Datavo, reducing TCO while optimizing HA performance and capacity.
- Transformed technical project management and new technology implementation processes at Flextronics, driving digital self-service capabilities, reducing costs, improving productivity, and accelerating speed of delivery.
- Played a key role in Gtran Wireless' start-up product development and integration during M&A with Flextronics.

Education & Credentials

Master of Business Administration (MBA), Cornell University, Johnson Graduate School of Management
Master of Science (MS) in Computer Science, University of Northern Virginia
Bachelor of Arts (BA) in Economics & East Asian Studies, Washington University in St. Louis
Certified Project Management Professional (PMP), Project Management Institute (PMI)
Microsoft® Certified IT Professional, SQL Database Administrator, Microsoft

Other Skills: enterprise architecture, build-vs-buy software evaluations, databases, enterprise architecture systems, web-based applications, network infrastructure, service/support desk, technology services, data collection, data management systems, applications, web sites, learning management systems, knowledge management systems, data governance, data management, enterprise systems, business systems, Human Resources, Proposal Management, remote work environments, strategic planning, outsourced services